<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <string-array name="reminders">
        <item><b>Appearance:</b> You take care of yourself and present yourself well.  Do something today to put your best (dressed?) foot forward—pay special attention to something you like about the way you look, dress, or groom yourself. </item>
        <item><b>Health:</b>  You are healthy and wellness is important to you.  Do something extra to take care of yourself—eat some fruit or veggies, take a nap, take a cleansing breath, and appreciate your healthy body and all it is doing for you.</item>
        <item><b>Motor skills/coordination:</b> You are agile and physically competent.  It may feel strange and awkward as your baby grows and your body changes, but you can adjust to this and keep your balance.  Try something out:  maybe some yoga, or a gentle stretching, and see how your centre of gravity is changing.  Appreciate your awareness of your body, and the little person doing somersaults within.</item>
        <item><b>Fitness:</b> You are fit and strong; this will help both you and your baby over the next few months and years. Do something physical you enjoy today—take a walk, or during your regular exercise, pause to appreciate your body—all the work it is doing to grow your baby, and how your care for yourself contributes to holding your baby in a safe, strong womb.</item>
        <item><b>Problem-solving:</b> You are clever and practical, able to solve the problems that pop up in life.  Think about the last time someone came to you with a problem, and you helped them to solve it.  How did you do that?  Are you intuitive, and the answer just seems to appear to you, or do you work things out logically, stepwise—or a bit of both?  What do you think is your best strategy for solving problems?</item>
        <item><b>Creativity:</b> You are imaginative, innovative, inspired.  This may show in creative work, or play, or in the way you go about your daily chores.  Put a bit of extra spark into something you do today—be playful, and surprise yourself!</item>
        <item><b>Verbal skills:</b> You are a good communicator—you express yourself well and get your point across.  Think about something you have to convey to someone today—either in person, or in writing—and stop to think through how you’ve done it, and what works well about that. </item>
        <item><b>Visual-spatial:</b> You are good at hands-on projects—making things work, putting things together.  Think about a project you are working on, or planning:  what is the next step?  What is satisfying about doing it?</item>
        <item><b>Memory:</b> You’ve got a good memory—think about how you use this skill to make your day better:  take a minute to  wander in your happiest memory; remember a friend’s birthday or something special you meant to do.</item>
        <item><b>Concentration:</b> You are a very focused person; you can use that to tune in to what you need to do, or what helps you, and screen out worries or troubles you don’t need to think about right now.</item>
        <item><b>Knowledge:</b> You have an amazing fund of facts—interesting things you know about. Consider Merlin’s advice:   “The best thing for being sad," replied Merlin, beginning to puff and blow, \"is to learn something. That's the only thing that never fails\” (T.H. White, The Once and Future King)</item>
        <item><b>Curiosity:</b> You are a mental explorer, curious and excited to find new things around every corner.  Think now, what have you noticed today that is fascinating, that deserves a second look?  Find out something new about it.</item>
        <item><b>Compassion and kindness:</b> You are considerate and thoughtful of others.  Do something—a smile, a supportive e-mail, a cup of coffee—for someone else today, and then see if you can do that for yourself, too:  give yourself a treat, a moment to appreciate something you’ve done.</item>
        <item><b>Friendliness:</b> You are friendly and approachable—say hello to someone new, or take a moment to ask a friend or acquaintance about themselves—and enjoy listening, seeing the spark that is genuine and interesting in that person, today.</item>
        <item><b>Loyalty:</b> You are a faithful and loyal person, and people know they can count on you to be alongside them in their times of trouble.  In your own difficult times, try to treat yourself as you would a friend:  what do you need?  Who are your loyal friends?  Look to your internal compass and see what is important to you—let that guide you in your steps.</item>
        <item><b>Honesty:</b> You are honest and trustworthy—people can count on your word.  Think about how you uphold this value in big and small ways in your life. </item>
        <item><b>Courtesy:</b> You are considerate and polite, careful about how you treat others and put them at ease.  Notice how you have done that today, pausing at a door, or responding with grace to an error.  Think about how this affects those around you. </item>
        <item><b>Discretion/tact:</b> You are tactful and discrete, aware of the potential impact of what you say.  Think about how this has shaped your relationships with people—do they respect your thoughtfulness?  What are the values that guide your discretion?</item>
        <item><b>Generosity:</b> You are a generous person—look around and notice what ways you are giving of yourself—of your thoughts, time, resources—to others. </item>
        <item><b>Helpfulness:</b> You are helpful—when you see a need, you do what you can.  How have you helped someone else recently?  Is there something you could do now to help, and still take care of your own needs as well?  </item>
        <item><b>Modesty:</b> You are modest—you know what you do well, but you don’t need to trumpet it excessively.  Remind yourself, though, of something you do well—it could be cooking, or writing, or sport, or lending an ear.  Think about how you have developed that over time, and how it feels to know you are doing something well.</item>
        <item><b>Sensitivity:</b> You are sensitive and attuned to emotions—this can be a source of strength, as you pick up on the nuances of feelings others may miss. In the midst of storm, take a breath and notice your emotions, and the emotions of others—pause and just watch these things, without having to respond. </item>
        <item><b>Forgiveness:</b> You can forgive and move on, preserving your relationships and building strength in them.  Forgive yourself, too, for whatever you might be picking on yourself for—you deserve the same compassion you give others. </item>
        <item><b>Leadership:</b> You are good leader—someone people respect, and you inspire them to get things done.  Think about how you are doing this today, in large or small ways—how can you be a role model, lead your family, friends, or colleagues in a positive direction. </item>
        <item><b>Affection:</b> You are warm and loving—take a moment now and tell someone you care for them—send a message or text, make a call, or say it in person. </item>
        <item><b>Persistence/perseverance:</b> You are persistent—you will stay the course, and do what it takes to get through to the finish line.  If there is something that is a struggle right now, think about times in the past when you’ve stuck with it, and been glad you did.  Is this a time like that?  What helped you at other times to carry on?  </item>
        <item><b>Faith:</b> Your faith is strong—remember what you believe in, and what is important to you; this will guide you in good times and bad. </item>
        <item><b>Sense of humour:</b> A laugh is worth a thousand words…you are good at finding the humour in between the lines.  Keep it up—if you can’t find it yourself, read something, watch something, listen to something funny.  Give yourself a giggle break. </item>
        <item><b>Patience:</b> You are patient—you can manage frustrations that might send someone else around the bend.  This is good—think how you do it, how you keep yourself on an even keel.  Remind yourself that patience is a virtue, but doesn’t mean you don’t have a right to expectations.  Use your patience to persist toward your goals. </item>
        <item><b>Reliability:</b> You are reliable and trustworthy—think about something you have done recently to act on your plans and responsibilities, to do what needs to be done. </item>
        <item><b>Responsibility:</b> You are honest and forthright, taking responsibility for your own actions.  Think about how this has shaped you and your relationships—do people trust you?  Do you feel strong knowing you have integrity? </item>
        <item><b>Courage:</b> “Whatever you can do, or dream you can do, begin it.  Boldness has genius, power and magic in it.”-Goethe </item>
        <item><b>Confidence:</b> Your confidence and faith in yourself can carry you far—remember the things you have accomplished in the past, and how you did them.  Make a plan for how you will take the next step toward something you anticipate being a challenge.  It might be breastfeeding, or juggling work and childcare, or a project at home.  How will you get started?  How will you keep going? </item>
        <item><b>Enthusiasm:</b> You approach the world with gusto and find the joy in life.  Look around you now and notice s is interesting, exciting, engaging. </item>
        <item><b>Flexibility:</b> You are good at adapting—you can see different options and aren’t afraid to change course and try a new strategy.  Look around at what you are doing now—work, or a project at home, or how you take care of your health—is it working?  Is there something you might try to do differently? </item>
        <item><b>Hopefulness/optimism:</b> You are an optimist, able to find hope even when dark clouds gather.  Remember that this is a strength for you—look for the light; you know it is there, and you can find it. </item>
        <item><b>Resourcefulness:</b>You are capable and practical—you know you will find a way to manage what you need to do, using what you have.  Think about how you’ve handled a recent challenge—small or large—when you found what you needed and used it resourcefully. </item>
        <item><b>Resiliency/toughness:</b> You are resilient—when things are hard, you have the tenacity to keep on trying.  Remember a time in the past when you ran into an obstacle, but persevered until you got what you needed. </item>
        <item><b>Stewardship:</b> You use your resources prudently, so you are more likely to have what you need, when you need it.  Think about how you have managed your resources—time, money, support—and how you can tap into reserves if you do have a need.  </item>
        <item><b>Thankfulness:</b> You are good at noticing and appreciating good things—and this is really good for you.  Stop and think about one thing that went well, or that you are thankful for, today. Let yourself think about this for a little while—what about it is good?  How does it feel to appreciate what you have?  </item>
        <item><b>Organisation:</b> You are good at preparing and planning, organising and arranging your life in a way that works for you.  If there is something that is feeling a bit out of control right now, think—is there a way you can do something to feel more prepared?  If so, what can you do?  If not, how can you let it go? </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="stressreminders">
        <item><b>Exercise: </b> Moderate exercise can help with anxiety and stress almost immediately, and if you exercise regularly, it can improve mood and energy levels.  Of course, while you are pregnant, you should check with your maternity caregiver, especially if you are starting something new—but even 10 or 15 minutes a day of walking (ideally outside, in the sunlight) can give you a boost.</item>
        <item><b>Mini-break: </b>If you find yourself getting wound up—or just have a few minutes between things—give yourself a mini-break.  Breathe, slowly, and stop:  focus on what is happening now, around you.  Look at a tree, or the sky, or even the lovely symmetry of the steering wheel…just be.  Choose a mantra—some words to say to yourself. </item>
        <item><b>Biofeedback: </b>Practice getting your body to settle down, with some kind of cue (that’s the feedback) about your level of physiological stress (that’s the bio).  With the __ module, it’s showing you your heart rate, so you can see how, when you breathe slowly and settle your thoughts, your body gets settled, too.</item>
        <item><b>Journaling: </b>Many people find that writing about their feelings and thoughts helps to make them clearer, and can sometimes help clear them out of your head.  Get a notebook, and write for 10 minutes—don’t worry about anyone else every seeing it—just write what you really feel. Or do it on a computer or tablet—whatever works for you.  Then close the book/file.  This can help for worries, frustrations, and confusion.</item>
        <item><b>Music:  </b>Whistle while you work?  Music can be a break in itself—take a few minutes and listen to your favourite song, or something inspiring—or it can add a background that helps make something else you have to do more positive—something upbeat while folding the laundry, or getting through the bills.  If you’re a singer, of course, this could be a more active option:  sing to yourself, practice some lullabies—or if you play an instrument, play what makes you happy.  One study found that 30 minutes a day of listening to music helped to improve the mood of pregnant women.</item>
        <item><b>Guided imagery:  </b>In guided imagery, you listen to a narration describing a relaxing scene, and imagine yourself in it—you can choose among several in the Imagery module—so you could transport yourself to walk along a beach, or in a favourite place, to take a fantasy break for a few minutes.</item>
        <item><b>Body scan:  </b>In a body scan, you take a few minutes to listen to your body, mentally experiencing how you feel, physically, in the moment.  You can do this on your own, or use an audio guide module, “Body Scan”</item>
        <item><b>Stretching: </b>Take 2/3 minutes and stretch whatever part of your body that feels like it needs it—feel your muscles as you raise your arms over your head, or move slowly and gently into an easy stretch.  Breathe.</item>
        <item><b>Relaxation breathing: </b>Take a few minutes and pay attention to your breathing.  Notice how as you breathe in, slight tension builds, and then as you exhale, your body relaxes.  Slow down your breathing, so that you breathe in slowly, hold it, and exhale.  If you like a structure, you can do what is called “square breathing”:  inhale to a slow count of four, hold it to a count of four, exhale to a count of four, wait to a count of four, and then start over.    Do that a few times.  Breathe from your belly (as much as you can, being as it may be a bit full right now).  Feel your lungs expand.  Especially pay attention to how the tension drains out as you exhale.</item>
        <item><b>Meditation:  </b>There are many traditions of meditation you may have tried or heard about.  Meditation practice can focus on a mantra (a special word), or mindfulness (paying attention to what is happening now), or breath, or a particular prayer.  If this interests you, read or learn more about a form of meditation that appeals to you.  Meditation can be done sitting, walking, standing, or even lying down. </item>
        <item><b>Prayer:</b>Prayer may be a traditional set of words for your faith, or a personal conversation with the divine.  Many people find prayer helpful in times of stress and change. You may pray for help, for strength, for peace, for a particular outcome, or use words as a way to express gratitude, faith, worry, sadness—any thought or feeling.  Consider whether you would like to learn a particular prayer, or find a book of prayers to read, or just take some time for connection with your spirituality.</item>
        <item><b>Massage: </b>Gentle massage can help with physical and emotional tension.  There are professional massage therapists who specialise in working with pregnant women.  You might also ask your partner for a massage—could be just your feet, or shoulders, or lower back, or whatever you are comfortable with.  One study taught partners of pregnant women to provide gentle massage, and found that not only did the women feel better, but the relationship improved. </item>
        <item><b>Yoga: </b>Yoga is a slow, meditative form of exercise that has been used with pregnant women across cultures and settings; studies have shown that many women feel this improves their mental and physical wellbeing.  Often special yoga classes are available for pregnant women.  Other, similar forms of meditative exercise include Tai Chi and Qi Gong.</item>
        <item><b>Gardening: </b>Getting out in the garden and helping things grow—or clearing away what shouldn’t be growing—might be what takes you out of your worries.  You can see what you’ve done.   Of course, be careful not to overdo it and strain something—but deadheading the roses might be just what the doctor ordered.</item>
        <item><b>Laughter: </b>Laughter may actually be the best medicine—or at least a good one.  Read a funny book, watch a comedy, go out with some friends who make you laugh.  Make a plan now—what is likely to tickle your funny bone?</item>
        <item><b>Reading: </b>Transport yourself with a story, or something that fascinates you.  For some people, reading is a trip away from the world, and that could be just what you need.  What is best for you—a book with short chapters, which you can read for 10 minutes?  Or a fantasy or thriller you can’t put down?</item>
        <item><b>Make a list: </b>If something is worrying you—if you are afraid you won’t get it done, or there just seem to be too many things you’re juggling, and it all seems impossible—sometimes making a list can help.  Break it down into doable bits, and tick them off.  Maybe even make a schedule of when you can do each. </item>
        <item><b>Call a friend: </b>For some people, it is really helpful to talk through their quandaries with someone who knows them—what is happening?  What shall I do?  Choose who you call thoughtfully—someone who is constructive, who will help you without ratcheting up the stress.  Sometimes, calling a friend might be for when you need NOT to talk about problems, but just to go out (or stay in) and do something you enjoy.</item>
        <item><b>Take a bath:</b>For some, a bath can be a time just for you, to relax, to feel warmth and nice smells, maybe with some bubbles or oil…focus on the now, not on planning or worrying.  If you find your mind going back to the stresses, play with the bubbles.</item>
        <item><b>Play: </b>What do you do that is playful?  Sometimes being with someone…a child, or a pet…who is completely absorbed in what you are doing—playing with a ball, or a toy, or blowing bubbles—can be a break from stress.  You could also play a game—in the real world, or on your phone or tablet.</item>
        <item><b>Go outside: </b>For many people, being outside, especially in a natural setting, can lift your mood.  Especially in winter, getting a bit of sun and air can also do wonders for your wellbeing, even if the weather is not the best.</item>
        <item><b>Feed yourself: </b>You (and your baby) need food to live and grow.  Remember to nurture  yourself with healthy, satisfying snacks.</item>
        <item><b>Create something [art, or craft, or food?]: </b>Create something [art, or craft, or food?]: <b></b>Making something can provide distraction, and the satisfaction of having a tangible product.  Could be sewing or knitting something for the baby, or baking, or drawing or painting or crafting—whatever is your thing.  You might even try something new—take a class, or look it up on the internet.  Trash to treasures?  </item>
    </string-array>

</resources>